I would like to talk to you about
أريد أن أحدثكم عن
a very special group of animals.
نوع خاص جدا من الحيوانات.
There are 10,000 species of birds in the world.
هناك 10,000 صنف من الطيور في العالم.
Vultures are amongst the most threatened group of birds.
والنسور من أنواع الطيور المعرضة لخطر الانقراض.
When you see a vulture like this, the first thing
عندما ترى طائرا مثل هذا، أول ما يخطر
that comes to your mind is, these are disgusting, ugly,
ببالك، أنها مخلوقات قبيحة، مقززة،
greedy creatures that are just after your flesh,
وجائعة تسعى وراءك لتنهش لحمك،
associated with politicians. (Laughter) (Applause)
تماما مثل السياسيين.(ضحك) (تصفيق)
I want to change that perception. I want to change
أريد أن أغير هذه النظرة. أريد أن أغير
those feelings you have for these birds, because
هذه المشاعر التي لديكم تجاه هذه الطيور،لأنها
they need our sympathy. They really do. (Laughter)
تحتاج إلى تعاطفكم، فعلا.(ضحك)
And I'll tell you why.
وسأخبركم لماذا.
First of all, why do they have such a bad press?
أولا، لماذا لدينا هذه الصحافة السيئة؟
When Charles Darwin went across the Atlantic in 1832
عندما ذهب تشارلز داروين في رحلة عبر الأطلسي سنة 1832
on the Beagle, he saw the turkey vulture,
على متن البيغل، رآى طائر البغاث،
and he said, "These are disgusting birds
فقال :"هذه طيور مقززة
with bald scarlet heads that are formed to revel in putridity." (Laughter)
ذات رؤوس قرمزية صلعاء ، شكّلت لتعربد في العفن".(ضحك)
You could not get a worse insult, and that from Charles Darwin. (Laughter)
لا يمكنك أن تتقبل إهانة كهذه، ومن تشارلز داروين أيضا.( ضحك)
You know, he changed his mind when he came back,
لكنه غير رأيه عندما عاد،
and I'll tell you why.
وسأخبركم لماذا.
They've also be associated with Disney — (Laughter) —
قد تم ربط صورتها بديزني كذلك - (ضحك) -
personified as goofy, dumb, stupid characters.
على أنها مخلوقات بلهاء وخرقاء وغبية.
More recently, if you've been following the Kenyan press
ومؤخرا، إذا كنتم تتابعون الصحافة الكينية
— (Laughter) (Applause) (Cheers) —
- (ضحك) (تصفيق) (تشجيع) -
these are the attributes that they associated
فهذه هي الصفات التي يوصف بها
the Kenyan MPs with. But I want to challenge that.
نواب البرلمان في كينيا. لكنني أريد أن أتحدى ذلك.
I want to challenge that. Do you know why?
أريد أن أتحدى ذلك. تعرفون لماذا؟
Because MPs
لأن نواب البرلمان
do not keep the environment clean. (Laughter)
لا يحافظون على نظافة البيئة. (ضحك)
MPs do not help to prevent the spread of diseases.
لأن نواب البرلمان لا يساهمون في منع انتشار الأمراض.
They are hardly monogamous. (Laughter) (Applause)
من الصعب أن تكون لديهم زوجة واحدة.(ضحك) (تصفيق)
They are far from being extinct. (Laughter)
هم أبعد ما يكونون عن الانقراض.(ضحك)
And, my favorite is, vultures are better looking. (Applause) (Laughter)
والأمر المفضل لدي، أن النسور تبدو أكثر وسامة منهم.(ضحك) (تصفيق)
So there's two types of vultures in this planet.
إذن فهناك نوعان من النسور في هذا الكوكب.
There are the New World vultures that are mainly found
هناك نسور العالم الجديد والتي وجدت بشكل خاص
in the Americas, like the condors and the caracaras,
بأمريكا مثل الكندور والكراكاس،
and then the Old World vultures, where we have
ونسور العالم القديم، حيث لدينا
16 species. From these 16, 11 of them are facing
16 نوعا، 11 منها معرضة
a high risk of extinction.
بشكل كبير لخطر الانقراض.
So why are vultures important? First of all,
إذن لماذا تبدو النسور بهذه الأهمية؟ أولا،
they provide vital ecological services. They clean up.
لأنها تقدم خدمات إيكولوجية حيوية، فهي تقوم بالتنظيف.
They're our natural garbage collectors.
فهي عبارة عن عمال نظافة طبيعيين.
They clean up carcasses right to the bone.
فهي تنظف الجثث حتى العظم.
They help to kill all the bacteria. They help absorb anthrax
تساعد على قتل البكتيريا، تساعد على امتصاص الجمرة الخبيثة
that would otherwise spread and cause
التي إن تم تركها، ستنتشر وتسبب
huge livestock losses and diseases in other animals.
في نفوق ومرض عدد كبير من الحيوانات الأخرى.
Recent studies have shown that in areas where there are
أظهرت دراسات حديثة أن المناطق
no vultures, carcasses take up to three to four times
التي لا يوجد بها نسور تستغرق الجثث مدة أكبر بثلاث أو أربع مرات
to decompose, and this has huge ramifications
لتتحلل، وهذا الأمر لديه تداعيات كبيرة
for the spread of diseases.
على انتشار الأمراض.
Vultures also have tremendous historical significance.
للنسور أيضا دلالة تاريخية كبيرة جدا.
They have been associated in ancient Egyptian culture.
فقد تم ربطها بالثقافة المصرية القديمة.
Nekhbet was the symbol of the protector
نخبت كان يرمز إلى الحامي
and the motherhood, and together with the cobra,
وإلى الأمومة، وبمعية الكوبرا
symbolized the unity between Upper and Lower Egypt.
كانا يرمزان إلى الوحدة بين مصر العليا والدنيا.
In Hindu mythology, Jatayu was the vulture god,
وفي الديانة الهندوسية، جاتايو كان النسر الإله،
and he risked his life in order to save the goddess Sita
وقد غامر بحياته لينقذ الإلهة سيتا
from the 10-headed demon Ravana.
من الشيطان ذي العشر رؤوس رافانا.
In Tibetan culture, they are performing very important
في الثقافة التيبيتية، يؤدون طقوسا مهمة
sky burials. In places like Tibet, there are no places
للدفن في السماء. في أماكن مثل التبت لا توجد أماكن
to bury the dead, or wood to cremate them,
لدفن الموتى، أو خشب لحرقهم،
so these vultures provide a natural disposal system.
وبالتالي هذه النسور تمثل نظام تخلص طبيعي من الجثث.
So what is the problem with vultures?
إذن فما هو المشكل الذي لدينا مع النسور؟
We have eight species of vultures that occur in Kenya,
لدينا 8 أنواع من النسور موجودة في كينيا،
of which six are highly threatened with extinction.
6 منها مهددة بشكل كبير بالانقراض.
The reason is that they're getting poisoned, and the reason
والسبب أنها تتعرض للتسمم، والسبب
that they're getting poisoned is because there's
في تعرضها للتسمم أن هناك
human-wildlife conflicts. The pastoral communities
صراعا بين الإنسان و الطبيعة. فالمجموعات القروية
are using this poison to target predators,
تستخدم السم لاستهداف الحيوانات المفترسة،
and in return, the vultures are falling victim to this.
لكن في المقابل، تقع النسور ضحية لذلك.
In South Asia, in countries like India and Pakistan,
في جنوب آسيا في دول مثل الهند و باكستان،
four species of vultures are listed as critically endangered,
4 أنواع تم إدراجها على أنها مهددة بشكل مقلق للانقراض،
which means they have less than 10 or 15 years to go extinct,
مما يعني أن أمامها 10 إلى 15 سنة للانقراض تماما،
and the reason is because they are falling prey
والسبب هو أنهم يقعون فريسة
by consuming livestock that has been treated
باستهلاكهم لحوما عولجت
with a painkilling drug like Diclofenac.
بمخدرات مسكنة مثل ديكلوفيناك.
This drug has now been banned for veterinary use in India,
هذا الدواء الذي تم منع استخدامه بيطريا في الهند،
and they have taken a stand.
وقد اتخذوا موقفا.
Because there are no vultures, there's been a spread
ولأنه لا توجد نسور، فقد انتشرت
in the numbers of feral dogs at carcass dump sites,
أعداد كبيرة من الكلاب الضالة في مواقع تفريغ الذبيحة،
and when you have feral dogs, you have a huge time bomb
وإن كانت هناك كلاب ضالة فإن لديك قنبلة موقوتة
of rabies. The number of cases of rabies
لداء الكَلَب، وأعداد حالات داء الكلب
has increased tremendously in India.
قد تزايدت بشكل هائل في الهند.
Kenya is going to have one of the largest wind farms in Africa:
كينيا الآن في طريقها لامتلاك أحد أكبر مزارع الرياح في أفريقيا:
353 wind turbines are going to be up at Lake Turkana.
سيتم تركيب 335 توربينة رياح تصل إلى بحيرة توركانا.
I am not against wind energy, but we need to work
لست ضد طاقة الرياح، ولكن علينا أن
with the governments, because wind turbines
نعمل مع الحكومات، لأن توربينة الرياح
do this to birds. They slice them in half.
تفعل هذا الأمر بالطيور، قتقسمها نصفين.
They are bird-blending machines.
فهي آلات مزج للطيور.
In West Africa, there's a horrific trade
في غرب إفريقيا، هناك تجارة مروعة
of dead vultures to serve the witchcraft and the fetish market.
للنسور الميتة التي تستخدم في السحر وتجارة الأصنام.
So what's being done? Well, we're conducting research
إذن فما الذي يتم فعله؟ حسنا، إننا نقوم بدراسة
on these birds. We're putting transmitters on them.
حول هذه الطيور، نقوم بوضع أجهزة إرسال عليها.
We're trying to determine their basic ecology,
نحاول تحديد أساسياتها الإيكولوجية،
and see where they go.
ونرى أين تذهب.
We can see that they travel different countries, so
نرى أنها تسافر لدول عديدة، لذا
if you focus on a problem locally, it's not going to help you.
إذا حاولت النظر إلى الأمر على أنه شأن محلي، فهذا لن يساعدك كثيرا.
We need to work with governments in regional levels.
علينا أن نعمل مع الحكومات على مستوى إقليمي.
We're working with local communities.
نحن نعمل مع المجموعات المحلية.
We're talking to them about appreciating vultures,
نكلمهم عن ضرورة تقدير النسور،
about the need from within to appreciate these
عن الحاجة الملحة لتقدير هذه
wonderful creatures and the services that they provide.
المخلوقات الرائعة والخدمات التي تقدمها.
How can you help? You can become active,
كيف لك أن تساعدنا؟ يمكنك أن تصبح فاعلا،
make noise. You can write a letter to your government
أحدث ضجة، يمكنك أن تكتب رسالة إلى حكومتك
and tell them that we need to focus on these very
وتخبرهم أنه علينا أن نركز على هذه
misunderstood creatures. Volunteer your time
المخلوقات التي أسأنا فهمها. تطوع بوقتك
to spread the word. Spread the word.
لتنشر هذه القضية. انشر الموضوع.
When you walk out of this room, you will be informed
عندما ستغادر هذه الغرفة، ستكون قد تعلمت
about vultures, but speak to your families, to your children,
عن النسور، لكن أخبر عائلتك وأطفالك،
to your neighbors about vultures.
وجيرانك عن النسور.
They are very graceful. Charles Darwin said
فهي رؤوفة جدا. قال تشارلز داروين
he changed his mind because he watched them fly
أنه غير رأيه لأنه رآها تطير
effortlessly without energy in the skies.
بدون أي عناء بدون طاقة في السماء.
Kenya, this world, will be much poorer
كينيا، سيصبح هذا العالم أكثر فقرا
without these wonderful species.
بدون هذه المخلوقات الرائعة.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم.(تصفيق)